Chapter 100. Leg and arm.
The Peekquad of Nantucket meets the Samuel Enderby of London.
Ship. Ahoy has seen the white whale.
So cried Ahab once more hailing a ship showing English colors bearing down
under the stern. Trumpetto mouth the old man was standing in his hoisted
quarterboat, his ivory leg plainly revealed to the stranger captain, who
was carelessly reclining in his own boat's bow. He was a darkly tanned,
burly, good-natured, fine-looking man of 60 or thereabouts, dressed in a spacious
roundabout that hung around him in festons of blue pilot cloth, and one
empty arm of this jacket streamed behind him like the embroidered arm of a Hazar's circoat.
Has seen the white whale?
See you this. and withdrawing it from the folds that had hidden it, he held up
a white arm of sperm whale bone, terminating in a wooden head like a
mallet. "Man, my boat!" cried Ahab impetuously, and tossing about the oars
near him. "Stand by to lower."
In less than a minute, without quitting his little craft, he and his crew were
dropped to the water, and were soon alongside of the stranger. But here a
curious difficulty presented itself. In the excitement of the moment, Ahab had
forgotten that since the loss of his leg, he had never once stepped on board
of any vessel at sea but his own, and then it was always by an ingenious and
very handy mechanical contrivance peculiar to the Peekquad, and a thing
not to be rigged and shipped in any other vessel at a moment's warning. Now,
it is no very easy matter for anybody, except those who are almost hourly used
to it, like whalemen, to clamber up a ship's side from a boat on the open sea,
for the great swells now lift the boat high up toward the bullwworks, then
instantaneously drop it halfway down to the Kelson. So deprived of one leg, and
the strange ship, of course, being altogether unsupplied with the kindly
invention, Ahab now found himself abjectly reduced to a clumsy landsman
again, hopelessly eyeing the uncertain, changeful height he could hardly hope to attain.
It has before been hinted perhaps that every little untoward circumstance that
befell him and which indirectly sprang from his luckless mishap almost
invariably irritated or exasperated Ahab. And in the present instance all
this was heightened by the sight of the two officers of the strange ship leaning
over the side by the perpendicular ladder of nailed cleats there and
swinging towards him a pair of tastefully ornamented man ropes. for at
first they did not seem to bethink them that a one-legged man must be too much
of a to use their sea banisters.
But this awkwardness only lasted a minute because the strange captain
observing at a glance how affairs stood cried out, "I see. I see a vast heaving
there. Jump, boys, and swing over the cutting tackle."
As good luck would have it, they had had a whale alongside a day or two previous,
and the great tackles were still a loft, and the massive curved blubber hook, now
clean and dry, was still attached to the end. This was quickly lowered to Ahab,
who, at once comprehending it all, slid his solitary thigh into the curve of the
hook. It was like sitting in the fluke of an anchor or the crotch of an apple
tree, and then giving the word, held himself fast, and at the same time also
helped to hoist his own weight by pulling hand over hand upon one of the
running parts of the tackle. Soon he was carefully swung inside the high bull
works, and gently landed upon the capston head. With his ivory arm frankly
thrust forth in welcome, the other captain advanced, and Ahab, putting out
his ivory leg and crossing the ivory arm like two swordfish blades, cried out in
his walrus way, "I I, Hardy, let us shake bones together. An arm and a leg.
An arm that never can shrink, do you see, and a leg that never can run? Where
did thou see the white whale? How long ago?"
The white whale, said the Englishman, pointing his ivory arm towards the east,
and taking a rofful sight along it as if it had been a telescope. There I saw him
on the line last season. And he took that arm off, did he? asked Ahab, now
sliding down from the capston and resting on the Englishman's shoulder as
he did so. I He was the cause of it at
least. And that leg, too. Spin me the yarn, said Ahab. How was it?
It was the first time in my life that I ever cruised on the line, began the
Englishman. I was ignorant of the white whale at that time. Well, one day we
lowered for a pod of four or five whales, and my boat fastened to one of
them, a regular circus horse he was, too, that went milling and milling round
so that my boat's crew could only trim dish by setting all their sterns on the
outer gunnel. Presently up breaches from the bottom of the sea, a bouncing great
whale with a milky white head and hump, all crows feet and wrinkles.
It was he, it was he, cried Ahab, suddenly letting out his suspended
breath. And harpoon sticking in near his starboard fin. I, I, they were mine, my
irons, cried Ahab exaltingly. But on.
Give me a chance then," said the Englishman good humoredly. "Oh, this old
greatgrandfather with a wide head and hump runs all a foam into the pod and
goes to snapping furiously at my fast line. I I see wanted to part it, free
the fast fish. An old trick I know him."
How it was exactly, continued the one-armed commander. I do not know, but
in biting the line, it got foul of his teeth, caught there somehow. But we
didn't know it then, so that when we afterwards pulled on the line, bounce,
we came plump onto his hump instead of the other whales that went off to
Windward, all fluking. Seeing how matters stood, and what a noble great
whale it was, the noblest and biggest I ever saw, sir, in my life, I resolved to
capture him, in spite of the boiling rage he seemed to be in, and thinking
the haphazard line would get loose, or the tooth it was tangled to might draw,
for I have a devil of a boat screw for a
pull on a whale line. Seeing all this, I say, I jumped into my first mate's boat.
Now, Mr. Mount Top's here, by the way, Captain Mount Top. Mount Top the
captain. As I was saying, I jumped into Mount Top's boat, which do you see was
gunnel and gunnel with mine. Then, snatching the first harpoon let this old
greatgrandfather have it. But Lord, look you, sir. Hearts and souls alive man.
The next instant in a gif, I was blind as a bat. Both eyes out, all be fogged
and be deadened with black foam. the whale's tail looming straight up out of
it, perpendicular in the air like a marble steeple. No use sterning all
then. But as I was groping at midday with a blinding sun all crown jewels, as
I was groping, I say after the second iron to toss it overboard, down comes
the tail like a lemur tower, cutting my boat in two, leaving each half in
splinters, and flukes first the wide hump backed through the wreck as though
it was all chips. We all struck out. To escape his terrible flailings, I seized
hold of my harpoon pole, sticking in him, and for a moment clung to that like
a sucking fish. But the combing sea dashed me off, and at the same instant
the fish, taking one good dart forward, went down in a flash, and the barb of
that cursed second iron towing along near me, caught me here, clapping his
hand just below his shoulder. Yes, caught me just here, I say, and bore me
down to hell's flames, I was thinking.
When, when all of a sudden, thank the good God, the barb ripped its way along
the flesh, clear along the whole length of my arm, came out n my wrist, and up I
floated. And that gentleman there will tell you the rest. By the way, Captain,
Dr. Bunger, ship surgeon. Bunger, my lad, the captain. Now, Bunger boy, spin
your part of the yarn.
The professional gentleman, thus familiarly pointed out, had been all the
time standing near them, with nothing specific visible to denote his
gentlemanly rank on board. His face was an exceedingly round but sober one. He
was dressed in a faded blue woolen frock or shirt and patched trousers, and had
thus far been dividing his attention between a marling spike he held in one
hand and a pillbox held in the other, occasionally casting a critical glance
at the ivory limbs of the two crippled captains. But at his superiors
introduction of him to Ahab, he politely bowed and straightway went on to do his
captain's bidding.
It was a shocking bad wound, began the whale surgeon, and taking my advice,
Captain Boomer. Here stood our old Sammy. Samuel Enderbe is the name of my
ship, interrupted the one-armed captain, addressing Ahab. Go on, my boy. Stood
our old Sammy off to the northward to get out of the blazing hot weather there
on the line. But it was no use. I did
all I could, sat up with him nights, was very severe with him in the matter of
diet. Oh, very severe, chimed in the patient himself, then suddenly altering
his voice, drinking hot rum toddies with me every night, till he couldn't see to
put on the bandages, and sending me to bed half seas over about 3:00 in the
morning. Oh, ye stars. He sat up with me indeed, and was very severe in my diet.
Oh, a great watcher and very dietetically severe as Dr. Bunga. Bunga,
you dog. Laugh out, why don't you? You know you're a precious jolly rascal. But
Eva head boy, I'd rather be killed by you than kept alive by any other man.
My captain, you must have heir this perceived respected sir, said the
imperturbable godly looking bunger, slightly bowing to Ahab, is apt to be
facitious at times. He spins us many clever things of that sort. But I may as
well say on passant as the French remark that I myself, that is to say Jack
Bunger, late of the Reverend clergy, am a strict total abstinence man. I never
drink water, cried the captain. He never drinks it. It's a sort of fits to him.
Fresh water throws him into the hydrophobia. But go on, go on with the
arm story. Yes, I may as well, said the surgeon coolly. I was about observing,
sir, before Captain Boomer's facicious interruption, that spite of my best and
severest endeavors, the wound kept getting worse and worse. The truth was,
sir, it was as ugly gaping a wound as surgeon ever saw, more than 2 feet and
several inches long. I measured it with the lead line. In short, it grew black.
I knew what was threatened, and off it came, but I had no hand in shipping that
ivory arm there. That thing is against all rule. Pointing at it with the marlin
spike. That is the captain's work, not mine. He ordered the carpenter to make
it. He had that club hammer there put to the end to knock someone's brains out
with, I suppose, as he tried mine once.
He flies into diabolical passions sometimes. Do you see this dent, sir?
Removing his hat, and brushing aside his hair, and exposing a bowllike cavity in
his skull, but which bore not the slightest scarry trace, nor any token of
ever having been a wound. Well, the captain there will tell you how that
came here. He knows. No, I don't, said the captain. But his mother did. He was
born with it. Oh, you solemn rogue. You You bunger. Was there ever such another
bunger in the watery world? Bunga, when you die, you ought to die in pickle, you
dog. You should be preserved to future ages, you rascal. What became of the
white whale? Now, cried Ahab, who thus far had been impatiently listening to
this byplay between the two Englishmen.
Oh, cried the one-armed captain. Oh, yes, well, after he sounded, we didn't
see him again for some time. In fact, as I before hinted, I didn't then know what
whale it was that had served me such a trick, till sometime afterwards, when
coming back to the line, we heard about Moby Dick, as some call him, and then I
knew it was he. Did thou cross his wake again? Twice, but could not fasten.
Didn't want to try to. Ain't one limb enough? What should I do without this
other arm? And I'm thinking Moby Dick doesn't bite so much as he swallows.
Well then, interrupted Bunger, give him your left arm for bait to get the right.
Do you know, gentlemen, very gravely and mathematically bowing to each captain in
succession. Do you know, gentlemen, that the digestive organs of the whale are so
inscraably constructed by divine providence that it is quite impossible
for him to completely digest even a man's arm? And he knows it, too. So that
what you take for the white whale's malice is only his awkwardness, for he
never means to swallow a single limb. He only thinks to terrify by faints. But
sometimes he is like the old juggling fellow, formerly a patient of mine in
Salon, that making believe to swallow jack knives. Once upon a time let one
drop into him in good earnest, and there it stayed for a 12 month or more. when I
gave him an medicic and he heaved it up in small tacks, do you see? No possible
way for him to digest that jack knife and fully incorporate it into his
general bodily system. Yes, Captain Boomer, if you are quick enough about
it, and have a mind to pawn one arm for the sake of the privilege of giving a
decent burial to the other, why, in that case, the arm is yours. Only let the
whale have another chance at you shortly, that's all. No thank you,
Bunger, said the English captain. He's welcome to the army has since I can't
help it. And didn't know him then, but not to the other one. No more white
whales for me. I've lowered for him once, and that has satisfied me. There
would be great glory in killing him, I know that, and there is a shipload of
precious sperm in him. But Harky, he's best let alone. Don't you think so,
Captain? Glancing at the ivory leg. He is, but he will still be hunted for all
that. What's best, let alone that oursed thing is not always what least allures.
He's all a magnet. How long since thou saw him last? Which way heading?
Bless my soul, and curse the foul fiends, cried Bunger, stoopingly walking
round Ahab, and like a dog strangely snuffing. This man's blood. Bring the
thermometer. It's at the boiling point.
His pulse makes these planks beat. Sir, taking a lancet from his pocket and
drawing near to Ahab's arm. A vast, roared Ahab, dashing him against the
bull works. Man the boat. Which way heading? Good God, cried the English
captain, to whom the question was put.
What's the matter? He was heading east, I think. Is your captain crazy?
Whispering Fidala. But Fidala, putting a finger on his lips, slid over the bull
work to take the boat's steering ore.
And Ahab, swinging the cutting tackle towards him, commanded the ship's
sailors to stand by to lower. In a moment he was standing in the boat's
stern, and the Manila men were springing to their oars. In vain the English
captain hailed him, with back to the stranger ship, and face set like a flint
to his own. Ahab stood upright till a long side of the peekquad.